{
  "reference_number": "12859",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "We have put dealing with this off for decades and now already we are facing consequences. NZ has currently very weak regulation in\n regards to environmental / climate protection and the Zero Carbon Act can provide a framework to begin to remedy this. The\n\n importance of this cannot be understated: it is an existential threat. The ways we can change our society to mitigate and adapt to\n climate change has the potential to create dozens of co-benefits and create a better, more equal, more connected society. Climate\n change is a feedback process from the atmosphere that we are out of kilter with the planet- we need to adjust our ways. The Zero\n\n Carbon Act is an important step towards this."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We need to set a confirmed target by the end of the year of net zero for 2050 at the very least. Even that is unlikely to meet any 1.5\n degree cut off points so we should be aiming for net zero by 2040 or net negative by 2050. Tackling methane will be tricky and need\n\n to be gradually and carefully managed, but if it can get to zero we can start thinking about being net negative as a country which\n would obviously be ideal. If we go for the two basket approach it is vital to have an ambitious, low target to stabilize methane at- e.g.\n 5% reduction will be pretty useless. The Climate Commission can look into optimal targets but we should err on the side of caution -\n\n this does not mean protecting agriculture, it means in terms of the massive risks if we give methane too much leniency. We need to\n have fast and dramatic action so that a lot of the decarbonisation happens earlier on, as it is the cumulative emissions that matter. We\n also need a holistic view, more so than ‘baskets’. We should aim to stay within all planetary boundaries, not just climate change- we\n\n also need to address nitrogen and phosphorus cycles, biodiversity etc."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "International carbon credits have been completely ineffective and also are unnecessary- we have every capability to do this without\n them (indeed if we can't, who can?) We also need to set an ambitious gross emissions reduction target- we can't rely on planting\n\n trees; though this is important at the end of the day we also need to decarbonize our transport and electricty systems. In terms of\n forestry offsets- we should also open up talks about credits for soil carbon sequestration. This could be a game changer for\n agriculture- if we are looking to lead the world in sustainable agriculture it is vital to have good soil, and good soil is full of carbon. If\n\n farmers have financial incentives to have healthy soil that will lessen the use of fertilizers and encourage more organic-based farming.\n We could also look at offsets in wetlands, mangroves, hemp - all of which sequester more than trees."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I agree that the Government and the Climate Commission should take the following factors into consideration when advising on and\n\nsetting budgets: moral responsibility to act • scientific knowledge regarding climate change • technology relevant to climate change\n• economic circumstances and the likely impact of a decision on the economy, as well as the competitiveness of particular sectors of\n\nthe economy (in terms of economic impacts from delaying action) and also realising economics is not all encompassing nor\nnecessarily always an appropriate tool, considering the massive risks to life and civilisation. • social circumstances and the likely\nimpact of a decision on fuel poverty (and awareness of international studies which show successful management of removals of fuel\n\nsubsidies when fuel poverty is countered with something like a cash transfer) • energy policy and the likely impact of a decision on\nenergy supplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy. benefits of resilience be being more self sufficient in terms of\n\nenergy"
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but it still emphasises economics over climate science. Unless economists start taking a more ecological viewpoint and\nconsidering externalities and the economy as part of a wider system, rather than all-encompassing, this could be dangerous in\n\nperpetuating current damaging institutions. It is important to have diverse experts in fields such as climate science and policy\ncommunication as well as economists. For example, previous governments have purposefully only looked at the cost of taking action,\nwhen they should also have looked at the costs of the impacts of climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Creating a strong Zero Carbon Act requires bravery and political confidence- with the changes we need, feathers will be ruffled and\n\nmany will complain. However, the necessity to go through with this with 100% commitment is so absolutely huge that it must\noutweigh all else. We have the potential, the capacity and the obligation to create a better future. You who have the power to create\n\nthis Act, we are counting on you. Please, have the courage to make this work !"
    }
  ]
}
